안녕, 멋쟁이
점심이야?
Hey, gorgeous! How's it going?
형광등 불빛 아래
바싹 마른 라면이야
Dehydrated Japanese noodles
under fluorescent lights.
최고급이지?
Does it get better than this?
질문! 요즘 누구 만나?
딱 맞는 사람을 발견했거든
Question: Are you dating anyone?
I met somebody who would be
perfect for you.
딱 맞는 다는 건 문제야
Perfect might be a problem.
종속적이거나
자기 파괴가 일어나
Had you said codependent
or self-destructive....
- 토요일 어때?
- 그럼, 좋지
-You want a date Saturday?
-Yes, please.
그 남자 귀엽고, 재밌어
He is cute.
-He's funny. He's
-He's a he?
- 그 남자라고?
- 응!
Well, yeah.
세상에! 내 생각에...
당신이 좋아 보여서
Oh, God! I just
You' re nice Oh, God.
화장실에 가서
변기에 머리나 박을게
Good, Shelly. I' m gonna flush myself
down the toilet now.
됐지? 안녕!
Okay. Bye-bye.
The One Where Nana Dies Twice
결국 라면이 속에서
얹혀 버렸어
It's hard to enjoy noodles
after that. Is that ridiculous?
기가 막혀서... 그렇게
생각했다는 게 말이 돼?
Can you believe she actually
thought that?
응!
Yeah.
나도 널 처음 봤을 때
약간 오해를 했었거든...
When I first met you,
I thought maybe...
... possibly...
...you might be.
You did?
그랬어?
그런데 피비 생일파티 때
You spent Phoebe's birthday
party talking to my breasts...
내 가슴을 쳐다보는 걸 보고
생각을 바꿨지
...so I figured maybe not.
Did any of the rest of you guys
think that when you first met me?
너희들 중에, 날 처음 보고
그런 생각 한 사람?
- 나!
- 응, 나도
-I did.
-I think so, yeah.
-Not me.
-No, no, me neither.
- 난 아냐
- 나도 아니야
물론 대학 시절에
수잔 살라도레는 그랬지만
Although back in college,
Susan Saladore did.
You' re kidding.
정말이야?
- 물론 아니라고 말해줬지?
- 아니
-Did you tell her I wasn't?
-No.
실은 나도 그 애와
사귀고 싶었거든
I wanted to go out with her too.
그래서 네가 버니 스펠만을
사귄다고 했어
I told her you were seeing
Bernie Spellman...
...who also liked her.
버니도 수잔을 좋아해서...
아주 흥미롭군!
Well, this is fascinating.
내 문제가 뭐야?
So what is it about me?
몰라
넌 똑똑하고 재미있어
I don't know.
You' re smart, you' re funny....
로스도 똑똑하고 재밌어
로스도 그렇게 생각돼?
So is Ross.
Ever think that about him?
-Yeah, right!
-What is it?
그럼 뭐냐구?
난 모르겠어
넌... 수준이 높아
I don't know. You just
You have a quality.
- 그래, 수준
-Yes, exactly.
-Yeah, a quality.
- 수준이 높지
- 맞아, 수준
수준이 높아?
다행이다
"A quality. " Good. I was worried you
were gonna be vague about this.
너희들이 내 수준을
모르는 줄 알았지
- 그게 장점이 될 수도 있어
- 뭐야?
I think this is gonna work for you.
-Excuse me?
-Sure, sure.
여자들이 널 친근하게 느끼면
마음을 금방 열지
Women find you less threatening,
they let their guards down...
바로 그때, 왕성한
이성애자임을 보여줘
...you' re like a stealth heterosexual.
여보세요?
레이첼, 파올로가
로마에서 전화했어
-It's Paolo calling from Rome.
-Oh, my God! Calling from Rome!
정말? 로마?
로마에서 전화를?
나도 할 수 있어
So he's calling from Rome.
I could do that.
당장 로마로 갈 거야
Just gotta go to Rome.
Your Dad just beeped in.
Can you make it quick?
너희 아빠 전화야
로마가 통화 중 대기상태야!
I'm talking to Rome.
로마와 통화 중!
Hey, Dad. What's up?
아빠!
무슨 일이죠?
Oh, God.
세상에!
Ross, it's Nana.
오빠, 외할머니...
왔어요
-How you doing?
-Hey, Dad.
- 안녕하세요?
할머닌 어떠세요?
So how is she doing?
The doctor says
it's a matter of hours.
의사 말이...
시간 문제란다
-How are you, Mom?
-Me? I' m fine, fine.
엄마 어떠세요?
난 좋다
와줘서 고맙구나
I' m glad you' re here.
- 머리 바꿨니?
- 네?
-What's with your hair?
-What?
-What's different?
-Nothing.
달라진 것 같아
- 아니에요
- 그렇구나
Oh, maybe that's it.
-She's unbelievable. Her mother's
-Okay, relax.
엄마는 잘 견디셔
외할머니가...
진정해, 진정하라구
여기 잠시 있자
We' re gonna be here a while.
넌 남자친구도 있고
직업도 있는 걸로 하자
We still have boyfriends
and your career to cover.
Oh, God!
하느님!
The fuzzy little mints
at the bottom of her purse.
할머니 가방 바닥에
있던 박하사탕!
Yeah, they were gross.
정말 징글징글했지
You know what I love?
제가 좋아한 건
할머니 사탕봉지예요
Her Sweet 'N Lows.
How she was always stealing them
from restaurants.
식당 같은 데를 가면
늘 많이 훔쳐오셨어요
Not just from restaurants,
from our house.
식당만이 아냐
우리 집에서도 가져가셨어
Mrs. Geller?
겔러 부인?
She looks so small.
- 너무 왜소해 보이셔
- 그러게
I know.
Well, at least she's with Pop-Pop
and Aunt Phylis now.
이제 저 위에서
필리스 숙모님과 계시겠구나
필리스 숙모도 돌아가셨어?
Aunt Phylis is dead?
응, 6년 전에
Yeah, for like six years.
- 난 왜 기억에 없지?
- 그걸 내가 아냐?
Where were?
Can we focus, please?
이번엔 기억해라
안녕히 가세요, 할머니
Goodbye, Nana.
안녕히 가세요
Bye, Nana.
오빠!
간호사!
Nurse!
무슨 일이니?
What is going on?
할머니 돌아가셨다고
간호사가 그랬죠?
You know how the nurse said
Nana had passed?
근데 아니에요
Well, she's not quite.
뭐?
What?
안 돌아가셨어요!
다시 부활하셨나봐요!
She's not passed!
She's present! She's back!
무슨 일이야?
What's going on?
돌아가셨을 텐데
She may have died.
그게 무슨 소리예요?
She may have died?
지금 알아보는 중이죠
We're looking into it.
보고 올게요
I'll go see.
이런 일은 처음이에요
This almost never happens.
이제 돌아가셨어요!
Now she's passed.
난 정말 알고 싶어
I just have to know, okay?
머리 모양 때문이니?
Is it my hair?
분명 그것 때문일 거야
머리 모양!
Yes, that's exactly what it is.
It's your hair.
그건 게이들 머리야
Yeah, you have homosexual hair.
- 왔니?
- 안녕
왔어?
할머님은...
So did she...?
두 번!
Twice.
- 두 번?
- 끔찍하다!
-Twice?
-Oh, that sucks.
너희들 괜찮아?
-You guys okay?
-I don't know. It's weird.
모르겠어, 이상해
이 세상에 안 계시다는 걸
느낄 수가 없어
I know she's gone,
but I just don't feel....
그럼 정말 가신 게 아냐
Maybe she's not really gone.
아냐, 돌아가셨어!
No, no, she's gone.
We checked.
확인했어
여러 번
A lot.
No, I mean, maybe no one
ever really goes.
내 말은...
이런 느낌이라는 거야
엄마가 돌아가셨을 때부터
지금까지, 내 곁에 있는 느낌이야
Ever since my mom died,
every now and then...
... I get this feeling that she's
right here, you know?
And Debbie, my friend
from junior high...
중학교 동창인 데비가
골프장에서 번개를 맞았는데
...got struck by lightning
on a miniature golf course.
I always get this strong
Debbie vibe...
노란 연필을 쓸 때마다
데비를 강하게 느낄 때가 있어
...when I use a little yellow pencil.
-I miss her.
-Here, Pheebs.
정말 보고싶다
여깄어, 피비
이거 가질래?
Want this?
고마워
-Oh, thanks.
-Sure.
오늘 아침에 새로 깎은 거야
I just sharpened her this morning.
난 그런 거 안 믿어
I don't believe any of that.
When you' re dead...
죽으면, 그냥 죽은 거야
땅에 묻히면, 벌레 먹이지
...you' re dead. You' re gone.
You' re worm food.
So Chandler looks gay, huh?
챈들러 게이 같지?
I don't know who this is,
but it's not Debbie.
이게 누군지 몰라도
데비는 아냐
아빠, 어서 결정하세요
Dad, let's just make a decision.
맞아, 어차피 땅 속에 묻힐 건데
그냥 기본적인 걸로 하자
You're right.
It's going into the ground.
We should get the most basic thing.
하얀 니스 칠을 한
물결무늬로 해요
"The non-protective corrugated
fiberboard with white laminate. "
Dad, we can't bury Nana
in a dresser from kea.
할머니를 싸구려 상자 같은데
모시고 싶지 않아요
This is why your mother
buys my clothes.
네 엄마가 내 옷을
사면서 그런 말을 해
난 쇼핑이 싫어, 싫어
I hate to shop. I hate it.
이런 걸 결정하고 사고 나면
정말 돌아가신 기분이 들까요?
Isn't this more about
the fact that...
...once you decide, it's like
acknowledging Nana's actually gone?
아니, 정말 쇼핑은 싫다
No, I really hate to shop.
-I thought it'd be a closed casket.
-lt doesn't mean she can't look nice.
관 뚜껑은 닫는 줄 알았어요
그렇다고 예뻐 보이시겠니?
Sweetie, you think
you can get in there?
얘야, 네가 들어가 보겠니?
제가 할게요
I don't see why not.
제 공구통이 여깄어요!
Here's my retainer.
I was just thinking...
생각해봤는데
-...when my time comes
-Dad.
내가 죽으면...
- 아빠!
- 잘 들어라!
Listen to me.
내가 죽거든
바다에 묻어다오
When my time comes,
I wanna be buried at sea.
You what?
뭐라구요?
바다에 묻히고 싶어
재밌을 거 같아!
I wanna be buried at sea.
It looks like fun.
뭐가 재밌어요?
Define "fun. "
하루만 시간을 내
보트를 빌리고, 점심 준비하고...
Come on. You'll make a day of it.
You'll get a boat, pack a lunch....
그리고 아빠 시신을
바다에 던지라구요?
And then we throw your body in
the water. Gee, that does sound fun.
참 재밌겠네요
다들 날 안다고 생각해
Everyone thinks they know me.
Everyone says I'm so predictable.
이렇게 말하지
잭 겔러, 평범 그 자체
내가 죽고 나면 다 이럴 걸
Maybe after I'm gone, they'll say,
" Buried at sea? Huh? "
그런데 바다에 묻혀?
That's probably what they'll say.
그렇게 말할 지도 모르죠
I'd like that.
그거 좋잖니?
안녕, 멋쟁이
-Hey, gorgeous.
-Hey.
안녕
Look, l' m sorry about yesterday.
어제 정말 미안했어...
아냐, 미안해하지마
Don't worry. Apparently, other people
have made the same mistake.
다른 사람들도 똑같은
실수를 할 뻔했대
Okay. Phew!
그럼 다행이네!
내가 왜 그렇게 보일까?
So, what do you think it is about me?
글쎄, 뭐랄까...
I don't know what.
You just have...
- 수준이 높아
- 그래, 수준
-...a quality.
-A quality. Great.
It's a shame. You and Lowell
would've made a great couple.
그나저나 안 됐어
로웰하고 잘 어울리는데
로웰?
Lowell? Financial Services Lowell?
That's who you saw me with?
재정담당 로웰?
그를 소개한다는 거였어?
What? He's cute.
- 왜? 귀엽잖아
- 그래
Well, yeah.
He's no Brian in Payroll.
브라이언 같진 않지만
Is Brian?
- 브라이언?
- 아냐! 모르겠어
I don't know. If you
were gonna set me up...
누군가를 소개하려면 최소한
그 친구 정도는 되야 한다는 거야
... I'd like to think it'd be
with somebody like him.
브라이언과는
정말 안 어울려
Brian's a little out of your league.
Excuse me. You don't think
I could get a Brian?
뭐라구?
내가 브라이언과 안 어울려?
그렇게 단정하면
브라이언을 만날 수도 있어
Because I could get a Brian.
Believe you me.
I'm really not.
이 말 취소야!
이거요?
This one?
아니
I've shown you every dress we have.
여기 있는 옷은
다 꺼냈어요
Unless you want her to spend eternity
in a lemon-yellow pantsuit...
엄마의 엄마가 가시는 길에
노란색 옷을 입혀드리기 싫으면
그냥 빨간색으로 하세요
...go with the burgundy.
우리가 뭘 고르든 엄마는
싫다고 하셨을 거야
Whatever we pick, she'd say
it's the wrong one.
맞아, 빨간색으로 하자
Right. We'll go with the burgundy.
탁월한 선택이십니다
나갈게요
A fine choice. I'm coming out.
Wait! We need shoes.
잠깐! 신발 골라야지
알았어요
이건 어때요?
-How about these?
-That's really a day shoe.
축제 때 신는 거야
Where she's going
everyone else will be dressier?
그럼 그 신발이
최고 아닌가요?
굽이 얇은 건 없니?
Could we see something
in a slimmer heel?
빨간색 파티용 신발은
없어요!
I have nothing in an evening shoe
in the burgundy.
I can show you something
silver that may work.
은색도 괜찮다면
그걸 보여드리죠
안돼, 빨간색으로 해야돼
-No, it really should be burgundy.
-Unless we go with a different dress.
아니면, 옷 색깔을 바꾸자
- 그럼 다른 걸...
- 그래, 맞아
안돼요, 잠깐만요
저 뒤에 뭔가 있겠죠
No, no, no. Watch this.
Wait, I may have something
in the back.
세상에!
Oh, my God.
너 괜찮니?
Is everything all right?
네...
할머니 사탕봉지요
Just Nana's stuff.
어때, 준비 다 됐어?
You guys ready?
엄마가, 머리 묶지 말라고
아침부터 전화하셨어
Mom called to tell me
not to wear my hair up.
이 비싼 귀걸이가 보이긴 해?
-Know my ears aren't my best feature?
-Some days it's all I can think about.
언젠가는 꼭 봐주마
안녕, 늦어서 미안해
옷걸이 찾느라 늦었어
I' m sorry l' m late.
I couldn't find my bearings.
귀걸이겠지?
You mean your earrings?
What did I say?
내가 뭐랬는데?
-Are these the shoes?
-Yes. Paolo sent them from ltaly.
- 바로 그 신발이야?
- 응
파올로가 이탈리아에서
보냈어
왜?...
What? We don't have shoes here?
미국엔 신발이 없냐?
안녕, 다들 준비됐지?
-Morning. We ready to go?
-Don't we look nice all dressed up?
다들 정장차림이라 멋지다
이런 말투도 문제지?
It's stuff like that, isn't it?
-lt was a really beautiful service.
-lt really was.
- 멋진 장례식이었어요
- 그렇지
얘야, 이리 와봐라
Come here, sweetheart.
You know, I think it's time for you
to start using night cream.
있잖니...
이제부터는
눈가에 아이크림 좀 발라
What?
왜?
아냐, 네 코트에서
해설가 소리가 나서
Nothing. Just that your coat
sounds like Brent Musberger.
-Check it out. Giants-Cowboys.
-You're watching football at a funeral?
이거 봐
자이언트 대 카우보이!
장례식장에서 미식축구를?
아니, 이건 예선이야
No, it's the pre-game.
I' m gonna watch it at the reception.
진짜 경기는
장례 피로연에서 볼 거야
넌 진짜 무서운 놈이야
You're a frightening, frightening man.
어머!
파올로가 준 신발인데!
Oh, no! My new Paolo shoes!
많이 안 망가지길 바래
I hope they're not ruined.
괜찮아?
정말 좋은 날이야!
God, what a great day!
왜? 날씨가 좋다구
What? Weather-wise.
그래
이 공기... 나무들...
I know.
The air, the trees.
할머니가 돌아가셨지만
모든 건... 그대로구나
Even though Nana's gone,
there's something almost life
- 오빠, 괜찮아?
- 로스!
Ross, are you okay?
괜찮아, 정말이야
No, l' m fine.
Just...
극도의 공포를
느끼긴 하지만...
... having my worst fear
realized, but....
걱정 마, 근육에
경련이 났나 보는 거야
I' m just checking to see
if the muscle's in spasm.
-What? What is it?
-You missed a belt loop.
왜 그래?
벨트 고리가 빠졌어
거기, 아파
Okay, it's in spasm.
경련이 일어났어
Here, sweetie. I took these
when I had my gall thing accident.
이거 받아라
심장에 통증 있을 때
먹던 거야
고마워요
Thanks, Mom.
- 먼저 하세요
- 죄송해요
Sorry.
Hi, l' m Andrea.
저는 안드레아예요
도로시가 어머니시죠
I'm Dorothy's daughter.
저는 챈들러인데요
도로시가 누군지 몰라요
Hi, I'm Chandler, and I have
no idea who Dorothy is.
Look who's up!
드디어 일어났네!
- 안녕...
- 기분 어때?
-How do you feel?
-I feel great.
아주 좋아
너무, 너무 좋아
I feel great. I feel great.
약 효과가 좋나봐?
Wow, those pills really worked.
처음 두 알은 별로...
다음 두 알에...
Yeah. Not the first two,
but the second two....
너희들 사랑해
너희들 최고야
I love you guys.
You guys are the greatest.
I love my sister.
내 동생도 사랑하고
I love Pheebs.
피비도 사랑해
That's so nice.
- 나도 좋아
- 야, 챈들러!
- 그래!
- 사랑해, 임마
I love you, man.
게이가 되고 싶으면
게이가 돼!
And listen,
if you wanna be gay, be gay!
난 상관 안 해
It doesn't matter to me.
네 말이 맞다
You were right.
레이첼!
레이첼...
널 사랑해
I do love you.
나도 널 사랑해
Oh, Ross. I love you too.
아냐, 진짜 사랑해
Oh, no, I really love you.
나도 진짜 사랑해
I really love you.
그 말, 안 믿어!
Oh, you don't get it!
그거 뭔가?
-What do you got there?
-Just a hearing disability.
이거... 보청기예요
현재 점수는?
What's the score?
17대 14로 자이언트 리드죠
3회 3분 남았어요
1 7-1 4, Giants.
Three minutes to go in the third.
신나는군
Beautiful!
- 피비, 과자 좀 집어줄래?
- 그래
Pheebs, could you maybe
hand me a cracker?
Your grandmother would've hated this.
할머니는 싫어하셨을 거야
네, 할머니가 주인공이어도
그렇죠
Sure. What with it being
her funeral and all.
이런 말을 하셨을 거야
No, I'd be hearing about...
"왜 햄에다 꿀을 안 발랐니?
꽃이 많지 않구나"
...why didn't I get
the honey-glazed ham.
Or I didn't spend enough on flowers.
Or she'd say:
그래서 말씀대로 하면...
"Why waste your money?
I don't need flowers, l' m dead. "
"넌 돈이 남아도니? 꽃은
필요 없어, 난 죽었어!"
That sounds like Nana.
정말 할머니 같아요
Do you know what it's like
to grow up...
엄마가 어떻게 컸는 지 아니?
할머니는 매사에 불만이셨어
...with someone who is critical
of every single thing you say?
충분히 이해해요
I can imagine.
난 그렇게 컸지만 긍정적인
인생을 살면서, 당당하단다
It's a wonder your mother
turned out...
...to be the positive,
life-affirming person she is.
That is a wonder.
대단하세요!
엄마, 궁금한 게 있어요
So tell me something, Mom.
If you had to do it all over again...
처음으로 돌아가서
할머니가 여기 계시다면
... I mean, if she was here
right now...
말씀 드릴 수 있어요?
...would you tell her?
T ell her what?
무슨 말을?
할머니가 엄마의 모든 걸
간섭하며 힘들게 한 거요
How she drove you crazy,
picking on every little detail.
예컨대, 머리 모양까지
Like your hair, for example.
내 말을 이해하지 못했구나
I'm not sure I know
what you're getting at.
Would things have been better
if you'd just told her the truth?
할머니께 말씀드리면
상황이 바뀌었을까요?
아니
그냥 넘어가는 게
더 나을 거야
Some things are better left unsaid.
맞춰 주는 게 좋은 거야
It's nicer when people just get along.
More wine?
와인 더 할래?
마시고 싶어요
Oh, I think so.
Those earrings look
really lovely on you.
귀걸이 참 잘 어울린다
Thank you.
고마워요
엄마가 주셨잖아요
They're yours.
Actually, they were Nana's.
사실, 할머니 것이었어
안돼! 안돼!
Now l' m depressed!
진짜 슬프네!
Even more than I was.
아까보다 훨씬 더
1학년 때 사진이야
배꼽티는 무시해 줘
Oh, look. My first grade picture.
Please ignore the Dy-no-mite T -shirt.
-Hey, who's this little naked guy?
-That little naked guy would be me.
발가벗은 이 꼬마는 누구야?
그 꼬마가 바로 나야
조그만 꼬추 좀 봐
Look at the little thing!
그래
그게 내 꼬추다
Yes, fine.
That is my penis.
현실로 돌아올래?
Can we be grownups now?
그 사람들은 누구야?
Who are those people?
-Got me.
-That's Nana right there in the middle.
- 몰라
- 할머니잖아, 가운데에
어디 봐
'자바조 식당에서 친구들과'
Yeah, let's see.
" Me and the gang at Java Joe's. "
모니카, 네가 할머니를
쏙 빼 닮았어
You look just like your grandmother.
How old was she?
이때 연세가 얼마야?
Let's see, " 1 939. "
- 1939년
- 39년이면...
- 스물 넷, 다섯쯤이네
- 맞아
Twenty-four, twenty-five.
친구분들이 좋아 보여
It looks like a fun gang.
Look, look, look!
I got Monica naked!
와, 이것 좀 봐
모니카 벗은 사진이야
- 그래?
- 어디 봐!
Let me see!
아냐, 이것도 나야
No, no. That would be me again.
뒤돌아서 뭐 하는 거지?
I'm just trying something.
- 안녕, 로웰
- 안녕, 챈들러
Hey, Lowell.
Oh, hey, Chandler.
재정 담당부는
요즘 어때요?
So how's it going in
Financial Services?
손바닥으로 하늘을 가리느라
정신이 없죠
It's like Mardi Gras without
the papier-mache heads.
- 거긴 어때요?
- 좋아요
How about you?
Good. Good. Listen...
쉘리가 나에 대해서
어떤 말을 했든...
...I don't know what Shelly told you
about me, but...
난 아니에요
... I' m not.
알아요
난 알고 있었어요
I know. That's what I told her.
- 정말이요?
- 네
Really?
알 수 있어요?
So you can tell?
대부분은 맞춰요
우리 같은 사람은...
Pretty much. Most of the time.
We have a kind of radar.
느낌이 와요
그럼 내가 어떤 수준이
높단 건?
So you don't think I have...
...a quality?
우린 동성애자를 그렇게 말하지만
그건 아니에요
Speaking for my people,
I'd have to say no.
아무튼 거기 친구
브라이언은 맞아요
By the way, your friend Brian,
from Payroll? He is.
- 그래요?
- 네
-He is?
-And way out of your league.
근데 둘은 안 어울려요
안 어울린다구?
Out of my league!
I could get a Brian. If I wanted to
get a Brian, I could get a Brian.
내가 맘만 먹으면
브라이언을 사귈 수 있어
안녕, 브라이언!
Hey, Brian.